<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <title>IP horizons</title>
    <link href="https://yngvarschnell.github.io/IPwebsite/feed.xml" rel="self" />
    <link href="https://yngvarschnell.github.io/IPwebsite" />
    <updated>2022-09-25T13:07:19+02:00</updated>
    <author>
        <name>Yngvar Schnell</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://yngvarschnell.github.io/IPwebsite</id>

    <entry>
        <title>Trademarks and Shipping</title>
        <author>
            <name>Yngvar Schnell</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://yngvarschnell.github.io/IPwebsite/trademarks-and-shipping.html"/>
        <id>https://yngvarschnell.github.io/IPwebsite/trademarks-and-shipping.html</id>
            <category term="trademark "/>
            <category term="shipping"/>
            <category term="TM"/>
            <category term="IP rights"/>

        <updated>2022-09-25T13:07:19+02:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://yngvarschnell.github.io/IPwebsite/media/posts/2/DCSA-TandT.jpg" alt="" />
                    Trademarks: the Legal Framework of reference As the aim of this presentation is to introduce some generic notions related to trademarks (henceforth “TM(s)”) and present a brief commentary on some uses of TMs which may be also relevant for ocean shipping carriers’ area of business.
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <img src="https://yngvarschnell.github.io/IPwebsite/media/posts/2/DCSA-TandT.jpg" alt="" />
                <h2><strong>Trademarks: the Legal Framework of reference</strong></h2>
<p>As the aim of this presentation is to introduce some generic notions related to trademarks (henceforth “TM(s)”) and present a brief commentary on some uses of TMs which may be also relevant for ocean shipping carriers’ area of business. I found it best to take, as the legal source of reference, the European Union REGULATION 2017/1001 (henceforth “EU Reg.”). This legal instrument applies across the EU and it regulates the subject matter in a way which is also similar to what one would encounter in most EU Member States’ own national legislations.  There are, however, also other international treaties on TMs (the Paris Convention, TRIPS of which single countries are signatories: many principles found in these conventions are iterated in the EU Regulation and in the EU Member States’ national laws already).</p>
<p>Why did the EU resort to a regulation as the legal act to govern this intellectual property right? Briefly, it can be said that it is because the barriers brought about by the territoriality of the national laws in the domain of TM could not be efficiently removed by the approximation of the laws of the Member States by means of EU Directives, so the idea was to create a unique system which would provide a single EU TM, with a single registration procedure and with protection and validity throughout the entire EU, thus by-passing potential divergencies in specific legal rules under the national laws (plenty more on the background of this EU Reg. can be found in the recitals to the regulation).  </p>
<p>To further contextualize, it can be interesting to point out that there are many legal sources which deal with TMs at international level: for example, the <strong>European Union</strong> is a signatory to the following international trademark agreements:</p>
<ul>
<li>the Trademark Law Treaty, signed on June 30 1995;</li>
<li>the Protocol Relating to the Madrid Agreement concerning the International Registration of Marks, to which the European Union acceded on October 1 2004; and</li>
<li>the Agreement on Trade-Related Aspects of Intellectual Property Rights, signed on January 1 1995.</li>
<li>Also, <strong>Switzerland</strong> is a signatory to the following trademark-related international treaties:</li>
<li>the Agreement on Trade-Related Aspects of Intellectual Property Rights;</li>
<li>the Madrid Agreement and Protocol Concerning the International Registration of Marks;</li>
<li>the Madrid Agreement for the Repression of False or Deceptive Indications of Source on Goods;</li>
<li>the Nice Agreement on the International Classification of Goods and Services;</li>
<li>the Paris Convention for the Protection of Industrial Property;</li>
<li>the Singapore Treaty on the Law of Trademarks; and</li>
<li>the World Intellectual Property Organisation Joint Recommendation Concerning Provisions on the Protection of Well-Known Marks.</li>
</ul>
<p>As mentioned, I will not deal specifically with TM under any other international treaty/national law in this presentation, yet, all the principles which are explained here and which are very basic to TM law, are applicable to the same extent under Swiss law or in the other EU countries (some more specific TM rules do diverge from the EU framework, for example international exhaustion of TM as compared to the EU’s regional exhaustion or other procedural rules regarding registration of TM and enforcement of TM rights).</p>
<p> </p>
<h2><strong>Why do we have TMs? Between law and economics and on the meaning of “monopoly rights” </strong></h2>
<p>Competition between enterprises which produce, sell or provide the same or similar goods/services has been sparked by mass industrialization and by the market driven economy (economy where trades between firms and households prevail over economy of production of goods and consumption of the same goods by the same individual). Goods (or services) which are competing and belong to the same category might different significantly in terms of price, quality, etc.: in order to enable buyers/consumers to orient themselves among all the different rival goods, the goods and services can be differentiated by attributing to them a “name”, the TM.</p>
<p>TMs allow buyers to recognize the goods/services based on the indication of origin of that good: consumers can then tell them apart from other competing goods/services. TMs also develop loyalty amongst some consumers to specific brands thus providing the producers with a powerful economic incentive to keep a similar standard of quality throughout its products and for the future in order to keep its customers. In other words, TMs encourage economic production of goods and exchange of services and ultimately growth of economic output.   </p>
<p>(Micro)economists purport that the purpose of a TM is the reduction of <em>search costs</em> amongst consumers: thanks to the TM, consumers do not have to compare different products as the TMs corresponding to the products that they are already familiar with will guide them into purchasing those same goods or different goods distinguished by that same TM as they associate with the specific TM a certain level of quality which they are ultimately looking for; another theory posits that we have TMs to <em>correct information asymmetries</em> in the market (i.e., a sort of correction of a <em>market failure</em>).</p>
<p>TM as a “<em>monopoly right</em>”: Lawyers refer to TMs, alongside with the other IP rights, as “monopoly rights” as the TM confers to the holder a right to exclude others from selling/trading a specific good that bears a sign identical or similar to the registered TM: however, in the language of microeconomics, a <em>monopoly</em> occurs only when the seller of a product is the only one in the market for that product and no close substitutes for that product exist: an invention (protected by a patent) or a literary/artistic work (protected by a copyright) can provide a monopoly to the seller who can then choose the price (monopolists are <em>price makers</em>) at which to sell its goods in order to maximize its profits (whereas in a perfectly competitive market the seller is a <em>price taker</em> and cannot choose the price but only chooses the quantity to produce so that the <em>marginal cost</em> to produce the last unit of good equals the <em>marginal revenue</em> raised by the sale of that last unit of good).</p>
<p>A TM holder is not necessarily a monopolist as close substitutes to the goods/services it sells can well exist (which cannot happen for inventions or literary works respectively protected under the law with patents or copyrights as the requisite is that they have to be “novel”). This is to say that economists and lawyers use the same expression, “monopoly”, in different ways.</p>
<p><strong> </strong></p>
<h3><strong>What is a TM under the EU Regulation?</strong></h3>
<p>(Article 4 EU Regulation)</p>
<ul>
<li>Trade mark : any sign which is capable of distinguishing the goods/services of one undertaking from the goods/services of another undertaking</li>
<li>Sign is an abstract concept: signs validly registered as TMs are usually (subject to the conditions mentioned at the below points): names, acronyms and other denominations (even fantasy names), figurative signs (such as logos/drawings), combinations of figurative elements (drawings) and names (very common), letters, numbers, sounds (jingles, perhaps the Microsoft chime when operating system starts is a registered TM?), colors (luxury brand Christian Louboutin’s red sole shoe is a TM; ocean carrier Maersk’s blue color is a color TM, see below more on color TMs)</li>
<li>Condition for the sign being validly registered as a TM: the sign must be <strong><em>distinctive</em></strong> (case law, both for individual EU countries and the EU, is plentiful on what specific signs are “distinctive”: when are letters of the alphabet distinctive? Are numbers distinctive (or only particular combinations of numbers?) Are basic colors distinctive? Or only specific chromatic combinations/tonalities? When do colors become distinctive (see below on this very question)?</li>
<li>Another condition: the sign must be able to be <strong><em>represented</em></strong> in the EU Register: “odors/smells/perfumes/scents” cannot be registered as an EU TM as, as of today’s state of the art technology, they cannot be “represented” in a clear and objective way and registering them would thus undermine legal certainty. However, in many EU countries, courts seem increasingly more open to the idea of providing TM protection to perfumes (ex multis, https://www.lexology.com/library/detail.aspx?g=56a10327-f4df-4288-abf7-0c6fd7882eed), or, at least, under the national laws of unfair competition (under unfair competition, even “assets” which are not protected as TMs can in fact receive protection from the unfair acts of a competitor).</li>
<li>Other conditions are listed under Article 7 EU Regulation (“absolute grounds for refusal”)</li>
<li>Registration: EU administrative law act/procedure which allows for the legal existence of the TM and the rights connected thereto: unless the TM is registered, no EU TM protection can be afforded. Several EU Member States do however provide also for effective “use” of the TM as a legal ground for the existence of the TM and its protection under their own legal systems (Germany, Italy, etc.).</li>
<li>Registration of the TM has to be requested in relation to a specific good or service pursuant to the Nice classification of the goods or services (Nice Agreement on the International Classification of Goods and Services)</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>The functions of the TM</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Identify commercial origin (protection against likelihood of confusion)</li>
<li>Guarantee consistent quality of the products (Protection against likelihood of confusion)</li>
<li>Advertising function and investment function (Protection against “dilution” - the whittling away of trademark distinctiveness)</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<h3><strong>Rights conferred by the EU TM </strong></h3>
<p>(Article 9 EU Regulation)</p>
<p>The preventive action of the TM holder concerns three different situations and can be exercised in any one of the following: (1) double identity (the TM holder opposes to the third party undertaking the registration of a sign or the infringing use of a TM which is identical to the one registered by the TM holder and which is requested to be registered for or is being used for goods/services which are identical to the ones of the registered earlier TM),  (2) likelihood of confusion (occurs when the TM holder opposes the registration of a sign or the use of a TM which is identical/similar to the earlier TM and requested to be registered or used for goods/services which are identical or similar to the ones for which the earlier TM is registered and because of this can cause a likelihood of confusion on the part of public of the territory where the earlier TM is registered), (3) dilution/misappropriation of well-known marks (the TM holder can prevent a third party from using a sign which is similar/identical to the earlier TM, regardless of the goods/services for which the sign is used, in case the registered TM has a reputation in the EU, i.e., the TM is a famous, well-known TM, like Coca Cola, Ferrari, etc.: the assessment is principally based on quantitative considerations regarding the degree of knowledge of the mark among the public, investments made by the TM holder in advertising its goods, the duration of the registration of the TM, etc.) The duration fo the protection term is 10 years, albeit indefinitely renewable.</p>
<p> </p>
<h2><strong>A selection of topics on TMs which are of interest for the ocean shipping’s business</strong></h2>
<p>In this section, in order to make more concrete examples, I will refer to and name specific container shipping companies: any reference thereto is purely for illustrative purposes. </p>
<h3><strong>Can a color as such be registered as a EU TM? </strong></h3>
<p>When we think of a color as a TM, we are not thinking of the color of the logo making up the TM (as in the case of, for example, the yellow color contained inside the MSC Mediterranean Shipping Company SA's logo) but we are referring to the color being <em>used as</em> a TM: so, for MSC, it would be the yellow color on an MSC container used to provide the MSC services.</p>
<p>Registering a color was already possible under EU law before the advent of the EU Reg., and the EU Court of Justice had admitted, in its case law, colors as TMs. However, interestingly enough, for some EU countries’ individual national laws (Italy or France, for example), a “color” per se can be registered only when it is not a “base color” but only when it is a particular tonality or a particular combination of colors: it is clear that this could lead to some coordination problems where a color is registered as a TM at EU level but under the national law that color could perhaps not be registered.</p>
<p>If we remind ourselves that a validly registered TM has to have the capacity of distinguishing the goods from those of competitors (Art. 4 EU Reg.), another issue with registering a color is the fact that a color is not regarded as a sign like a logo: it is assumed (under constant EU case law) that a logo has an <em>ab initio</em> distinctiveness, whereas the same cannot be said about a color: a color is not inherently distinctive and if we want to register it, we have to prove that it has the capacity to distinguish goods; as colors, or chromatic combinations are initially available to anyone, it is the effective use which will make the specific color for which registration is requested acquire the ability to distinguish the goods in that color (so-called <em>secondary meaning</em>). Perhaps the most interesting case of color TM registration is the famous Christian Louboutin’s red shoe: <a href="https://www.worldtrademarkreview.com/single-colour-trademarks-enforcement-christian-louboutins-red-sole-trademark">https://www.worldtrademarkreview.com/single-colour-trademarks-enforcement-christian-louboutins-red-sole-trademark</a>.</p>
<p>In the world of shipping law, A.P. Møller-Mærsk’s successful registration (albeit, under Danish law) as a Danish color TM of the color 'Pantone Maersk Blue' in class 39 for "sea freight transport" has made headlines. In Denmark, it is only the second time that the Danish Patent and Trademark Office has afforded TM protection to a color. The ocean carrier had to prove, just as it would have had, had it applied for an EU TM, the consistent, prolonged use of the color: Maersk documented that it had been using its traditional blue color since 1886 for its containers and vessels and attached to its application even evidence of a demoscopic study evidencing that an unaided 88% of the relevant market public would associate the color specifically with Maersk. On these grounds, it is possible to see how the Danish national TM register office was satisfied as for the distinctiveness requirement. As mentioned above, the mere fact that the TM is used only in one EU Member State would not prevent the enterprise to seek TM registration at EU level (by means of a EU TM), so, in theory, Maersk could also obtain EU TM registration of its color. Here below the color registered as TM by Maersk.</p>
<p> </p>
<h3><strong>The use of the sign "MSC" by a company not associated with MSC Mediterranean Shipping Company SA </strong></h3>
<p>The proprietor of the TM can exclude third parties from using a sign (a sign that is used as a TM but also a sign that is used as a company name or trade name (Art.9 (3) letter (d) EU Reg.)  that is identical or similar to the TM – in relation to identical or similar products or services – in the course of trade: so, for example, third parties cannot use a sign identical or similar to "MSC Mediterranean Shipping Company" for the trade of products/services identical or similar to the ones for which the MSC TM is registered. The not-for-profit organization “Marine Stewardship Council”, which uses a TM consisting of the letters, in sequence, M, S and C, can lawfully promote its operations also in the territory where the liner MSC has registered its TM as the services for which it is registered are <em>not the same</em> ones as those of ocean carrier MSC: what is more, it could be argued that perhaps the activities of this organization are not carried out “in the course of trade” (Art. 9(2) Eu Reg.) as its activities are non-profit and therefore they would not be caught under the regulation.</p>
<p>An interesting observation can arise when thinking of what parts of the TM third parties cannot use: it would be unreasonable not to allow third parties ocean carriers to register a TM containing the word “shipping” or the word “company” as the law does not allow for the registration of generic names (Art. 7 (1) letter (c) EU Reg.). If one were to take each word making up the MSC TM, it would be evident that none of these words is a word which, in of itself, possesses a distinctive character; it is arguable that each one of these words can be used by a competitor who intends to register a mark (for the same/similar services offered by MSC). It is the combination of these words which cannot be lawfully used by a third party as this very combination possesses a sufficient degree of distinctiveness.</p>
<p> </p>
<h3><strong>Can a company place their own trademark on third-party goods which they have possession of and use by virtue of a rental agreement (or other commercial agreement for the use of such third-party goods)? </strong></h3>
<p>Can, for example, CMA CGM (the world's third largest container shipping company) place its TM on third party owned containers? It is clear that with this question we are not considering a TM whose function is to distinguish the origin of the <em>goods</em> themselves, but we are addressing a TM for <em>services</em>: the containers are not being sold, so the function of the CMA CGM TM on the containers is not to inform the consumer of the <em>origin of the containers</em>, yet to inform the consumer (the merchant) of the <em>origin of the carriage services</em> (here what is important is that the provider of the services not use a TM that is similar to the one of a competitor).</p>
<p>Had the containers been marked with CMA CGM's TM and been sold as such by a third party, the producer of the containers would have been able to claim TM infringement as the potential buyer could have reasonably believed that the containers originated from CMA CGM. This is also why we see in terms and conditions of chartered vessels, that the charterer, once the charterparty agreement has expired, has to remove its TM from the vessel: “<em>The Owner agrees that the Charterer may display the Charterer's logo and the Charterer's designated name on the Vessel during the Charter Term. If the Owner retains ownership of the Vessel after the Charter Term, it agrees not to display the Charterer's logo. If the Owner sells the Vessel after the Charter Term it will require the purchaser to agree not to use the Charterer's name or logo in connection with the Vessel</em>” (from “BAREBOAT CHARTER AGREEMENT "CHAMPIONSHIP"“ signed between Cargill as the owner and a charterer).</p>
<h2><strong>Use of a TM under the EU Regulation and some exceptions </strong></h2>
<h3><strong>The appearance of MSC-branded containers in the music video by Coldplay: is the music band <em>using</em> MSC’s TM? </strong></h3>
<p><strong> </strong>It can be argued that even though the MSC TM does appear on the video (<a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=gXgf5smLEgQ">https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=gXgf5smLEgQ </a>), there is no use of the MSC TM in the typical function that a sign protected as a TM under the law would be used for: the MSC TM is not used to distinguish the product (the music video) amongst other competitors (other producers of music videos or other singers) and the test of the average informed consumer of musical videos would prove that the consumer would not reasonably believe that the video originates from MSC or that any link or association should be established between the company that produced the video or the singer and MSC. The artist Andy Warhol used, as a subject of his pop art paintings, the Campbell’s tomato soup cans: could it be inferred that the artist’s works were infringing the company Campbell’s TM?</p>
<p>What about a photographer who publishes and sells pictures of vessels (or other equipment) bearing, for example, the CMA CGM service TM? If it is established that the TM is not used by the photographer in one of its typical functions, then the photographer can freely sell the pictures without infringing any CMA CGM’s TM: even if CMA CGM is in the business of publishing marketing material (more correctly, if CMA CGM has registered its TM also for this specific class of goods/services), the simple publishing of the CMA CGM vessels pics by the photographer could hardly be seen as use of CMA CGM’s TM. The photographer is using the CMA CGM TM in a non-distinctive way (Art. 14(1) EU Reg.). The visible CMA CGM TM on the vessels could not be associated automatically, on the part of the average informed consumers, with the fact that the pics themselves originate from CMA CGM; furthermore, it is known to the buyers of these photographs that the photographer has an interest in taking a pic and publishing it unaltered, faithful to what she sees, therefore also with the CMA CGM TM on the photographed vessel. It would be different if an CMA CGM TM were placed “on top” of the pic itself, in a position which is customary to carry the photographer’s logo/TM. However, if the registered TM has a reputation in the EU (to bear in mind that a TM is just registered as a TM, there is not such registration for a “TM that has a reputation”, as the possession of reputation will have to be proven on a case by case basis either in opposition to a registration request by a third party or in a claim for infringement of TM by the third party) , then the TM cannot be used for competing goods/services <em>and not even</em> for services or goods that are not related to the ones offered by the TM holder.</p>
<h3><strong>More in general on the non-distinctive/referential and descriptive uses: Article 14(1) letters (b), (c) EU Regulation</strong></h3>
<p><strong> </strong>A third party can use a TM, <em>even if it has a reputation</em>, in the context of a “descriptive or referential use”: third party capsules can be advertised as “compatible with Nespresso machines” and the producer of such capsules can then use the TM Nespresso: “Nespresso” is a registered TM but the use made here by the third party serves to indicate the correct destination of its own capsules (furthermore, for what patent law is concerned, even if Nespresso has protected its own capsule invention by means of a <em>patent</em>, this does not mean that Nespresso can exclude a potential competitor from addressing the same problem by means of an alternative technical solution, i.e., the capsule from the third party which is likely based on an alternative solution).   </p>
<p>Another example: an independent auto repair shop, if specialized in fixing Ferrari cars, will be entitled to use the Ferrari TM in advertising its services, online or on paper leaflets, to the public. It will have to be careful to use the TM only in the measure for which it is strictly necessary as any unnecessary use may be seen as potentially creating a likelihood of confusion (amounting to TM infringement) or, for TMs which have a reputation, unfairly free-riding on the notoriety and distinctiveness of the Ferrari brand to attract customers to its business (amounting to TM infringement and also tantamount to “reputation parasitism”). In this latter instance, one can appreciate that the function of the TM that the law protects is not only the function of origin (allowing the general public to orientate their purchases based on the association of specific qualities or characteristics to a specific TM) but rather more the function of advertising: the attractiveness of the TM needs protection, especially for brands which have a reputation, and it should not be exploited by third-parties to promote their own goods or services, even when the risk of confusion is minimal: a counterfeit watch bearing the renowned Rolex TM and displayed on a shop-window albeit accompanied by a “disclaimer” informing the potential buyer that the watch is a knock-off (thus preventing any reasonable confusion from occurring at point of sale), will still attract many consumers’ attention firstly onto the TM on the dial of the watch (as, this is where the consumer’s attention will firstly be placed at) and only, at a later stage, will the consumers read the warning about the watch’s being non-genuine merchandise: however, in the meantime, the seller of the counterfeit Rolex will have already achieved its goal, as some of the consumers may have, nevertheless, noticed other watches or walked into the seller’s shop and determined themselves to look for other items inside the shop: the free-riding on the notorious TM does not have to culminate in the sale of the goods of the third party free rider in order to speak of TM infringement. As a matter of fact, the non-authorized seller will have attracted potential customers to its business by leeching off on the fame of a good which is distinguished by a TM that has a reputation.  </p>
<p> </p>
<h3><strong>More on non-distinctive/referential/descriptive uses exceptions: on TM use on toy scale models of vessels </strong></h3>
<p>Can manufacturers produce and market in scale toys/models of cars/vessels in the European Union without the license of the owner of the TM which appears on the in scale models? In other words, is the producer of the models <em>using</em> the third-party TM? Let’s suppose, for instance, that Hapag-Lloyd (the German largest container transportation company) has registered its TM also in the sector of in scale models/toys: would Hapag-Lloyd be able to prevent a third-party from affixing the Hapag-Lloyd TM on the vessel in scale replicas?</p>
<p>The producer of the TM has an incentive in creating and producing the toys/in scale models as close as possible to reality as their faithful rendition would make the products more interesting to the buyers, especially for more sophisticated buyers who are purchasing the in scale models outside of the context of toys. Would the buyers of the products believe that they originate from the TM owner?</p>
<p>In a case before the ECJ (C-48/05 – Opel/Autec), which saw a manufacturer of scale toy car models, Autec, opposed to German car-maker Opel, the European judge pronounced that “<em>the average consumer of the products of the toy industry</em><em> and in scale models</em><em>,</em><em> is</em><em> normally informed and reasonably attentive and circumspect, is used to scale models being based on real examples and even accords great importance to absolute fidelity to the original, so that that consumer will understand that the Opel logo appearing on Autec’s products indicates that this is a reduced-scale reproduction of an Opel car</em>”.</p>
<p>In my opinion, it could be even further argued that the Opel logo on the replica toy model is not serving any TM function, therefore any reproduction thereof should not be treated under the TM law: it is in fact ordinary, in the car sector to associate the logo on the chassis of the car with the producer of that car (origin function of the TM), so that the logo will indeed serve as a TM; on the other hand, the toy cars (or other memorabilia) is a different industry in which it is not customary to use the logo of a car-maker (Opel or others) positioned on the chassis of the toy vehicle to indicate the origin of the particular model, but rather, to provide the toy model with a higher accuracy/reality feel which makes the toy more appealing: the buyer of the toy will be in fact able to easily flip the in scale car (not able to do this with a real car so easily!!) and the bottom will reveal the TM of the producer – and, in all likelihood (even though not considered in the ECJ’s commentary on the Autec-Opel affair), the packaging of the in scale model will have already informed the buyer of the origin of the product: the manufacturer will have placed its TM on the packaging in which the toy is sold. The same considerations can be made with regards to Hapag-Lloyd’s TM affixed on in scale vessel or containers models or in other cases like video games which faithfully reproduce the TM of a car maker or other goods. The analogy can be stretched further to cases like when the doctor prescribes a specific pharmaceutical: the doctor will use the TM of the pharma company but it will not do so to promote its services and, generally, will not create any confusion at the consumers’ level as for the origin of the drugs prescribed.</p>
<p>Therefore, in broader terms, it can be said that every time the third party uses the TM to convey some information about its own products/services to the buyer, the legality of the said use can be subsumed under the exception of the referential/descriptive use or non-distinctive use of the TM, which is specifically provided for under Art. 14 of the EU Regulation. The application of the above exception would not prevent the third party to go exempt from any liability in the following cases (A) and (B).  (A) if the TM refers to a luxury good, then its referential use by the non-owner for the advertisement of (i) services connected to the luxury goods (ex: advertisement of repair services of luxury items which takes place in a way that is detrimental to the image of luxury and exclusivity of the brand) or for (ii) the resale of the luxury goods (luxury bags resold at discount stores), would infringe upon the TM as the circumstances of such TM use would damage the aura of luxury and fame of the product (this is what in the US TM law is referred to as “TM dilution by tarnishment”, i.e., the luxury goods are portrayed in an unwholesome or distasteful context that is likely to reflect adversely upon the TM owner’s product). There is case law aplenty (not just in EU) and many more pending cases, where luxury brands sue resellers on the grounds that the modalities by which they present the luxury goods detracts from the aura of luxury of the goods. To be noted here that, in the example above of the resale of the luxury goods in ways which harm the repute of the brand, the principle of the exhaustion of the TM right (Article 15 EU Reg.) would not operate as this case would be treated as a legitimate reason for the TM owner to oppose further commercialization of the goods bearing its TM.  (B) In case the goods sold (or services rendered) which bear the third party TM are of inferior quality, then the TM owner might object to the use of its TM on grounds of damage to its image/reputation (and in this case, the TM need not be referred to a luxury brand necessarily): this case could also be relevant for Hapag-Lloyd, in case the producer of in scale vessel models distributes goods which are of inferior quality than what is standard in the industry of reference for those goods.</p>
<p> </p>
<p> </p>
<p><strong> </strong></p>
<p> </p>
<p> </p>
<p> </p>
<p> </p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
</feed>
